Finding Aid for the Alberto Sánchez de Iriarte Collection [Spanish Civil War]
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Alberto Sánchez de Iriarte Collection
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0202
Biography
Alberto Sánchez de Iriarte, better known as Dr. Mirabel, or Fantasio, was born in Bogotá, Colombia in 1886. He was a well-known Colombian humorist, writer, historian and journalist, who wrote for the Colombian magazines Cromos and Revista Contemporánea and for the newspapers El Tiempo, El Espectador and Mundo al dia. He also employed the pseudonyms Maese Floridor and Sz. From 1910 to 1915 he directed the magazine El Gráfico, one of the most important publications in the history of Colombian journalism. During the 1920s, he was a principal collaborator of Cromos magazine. (Muñoz, 1958) and (Vallejo Mejía, 2004)
In the early 1930s he was designated First Secretary of the Colombian Legation in Madrid. During the time he was posted in Spain he participated in the following activities. He represented Colombia at the Pan-American Postal Congress in January 1932, with the goal of consolidating the Americas and Spain into a single postal territory. He was awarded the Order of Isabel the Catholic by the Spanish government in recognition of his outstanding performance at the congress (ABC Sevilla, 1932). He also represented Colombia at the International Radiotelegraph Conference in Madrid, September 1932. The conference was intended to fuse The International Telegraph Union and the International Radiotelegraph Union into a single organization: the International Telecommunication Union. In 1936 the Republic of Colombia decided to temporarily shut down the Embassy of Colombia in Spain due to the outbreak of the Spanish Civil War. It was then that Sánchez de Iriarte returned to Colombia and continued his passion for writing.
He is considered a pioneer of modern journalism in Colombia for his concern with issues of everyday life. His writing style was akin to the modernist school. According to Maryluz Vallejo, Director of the Colombian magazine Directo Bogotá he alternated between chronicling social customs of the capital city, Santa Fé de Bogotá, with historical and literary chronicles incorporating international current affairs of the time. He employed a wide variety of narrative structures, usually presented in a newspaper serial format, with dialogues and a reconstruction of scenes. His work has not been published as a compilation and he appears in only a few anthologies of Colombian writers. (Hoyos, 2009, p. 433)
Works Cited
ABC Sevilla. (1932, January 17). p. 28.Hoyos, J. J. (2009). La pasión de contar: el periodismo narrativo en Colombia, 1638-2000. Colombia: Univeridad de Antioquia.
Muñoz, G. O. (1958). Seudónimos de escritores colombianos. Thesaurus. Retrieved March 2012, from Centro Virtual Cervantes: http://cvc.cervantes.es/lengua/thesaurus/pdf/13/TH_13_123_120_0.pdf
Vallejo Mejía, M. (2004). La Crónica en Colombia: Medio Siglo de Oro. Retrieved March 2012, from http://www.scribd.com/doc/60278681/La-Cronica-en-Colombia-Medio-Siglo-de-Oro
Provenance
The Spanish Civil War Collection appears to have been created by Alberto Sánchez de Iriarte, also known as Dr. Mirabel. The collection contains a series of documents from Spain and Latin America, with many documents from Colombia. The materials also contain elements from The Spanish Republic, which was prior to the Spanish Civil War. Many of the materials were gathered by Sánchez de Iriarte when he was the Secretary of the Colombian Legation to the Spanish Republic in the 1930s. After the fall of the Spanish Republic in the late 1930s the papers were transferred from the embassy along with the entire legation back to Colombia. The items were then probably kept in a storeroom in the Ministry of Foreign Relations in Bogotá, Colombia.
Dr. J. León Helguera, a professor of History at Vanderbilt University and a specialist in Colombian history purchased this collection from a book dealer in Colombia and transferred it to the United States. In the early 1970s he donated the collection to the Joint University Libraries-Special Collections.
Scope and Content
The Alberto Sánchez de Iriarte Collection is divided in eight series and is comprised of 21 archival boxes or 10.38 linear feet.
Series I: Newspaper Clippings, Spain: Includes various selections of newspaper clippings from the most important newspapers of Spain at the time. The majority of the clippings are from the newspapers ABC and El Sol but also includes clippings from La Vanguardia, Ya, Tiempo among others. The clippings are arranged by publication date, ranging from 1919-1943. The subject matter is varied – economy, politics, religion, tourism, culture and arts in Spain. This section also includes newspaper clippings in French from 1920-1936 and scrapbooks of newspaper articles kept by Sánchez de Iriarte. The articles contained in the scrapbooks are dated from 1935-1939 with the subject matter mostly related to the Spanish Civil War.
Series II: Newspaper Clippings, Latin America: This series contains a wide assortment of newspaper clippings mostly from Colombian newspapers such as Mundo al Día, Tiempo, and El Espectador but also includes clippings from Argentina, Chile, Mexico, and Peru. The clippings are arranged by publication date, ranging from 1910-1946. The subject matter is varied – economy, politics, religion, tourism, culture and arts. Most articles are related to events related to the Spanish Republic and the Spanish Civil War time period. This section also includes newspaper and magazine clipping scrapbooks of articles kept by Sánchez de Iriarte. The articles contained in the scrapbooks are dated from 1916-1935, the topics they cover are about economy (banking, budget, money, gold), diplomacy, and literature (articles about H.G. Wells.)
Series III: Magazine Fragments, Spain: This series includes a wide variety of selected articles from Spanish magazines. The fragments are arranged alphabetically and by publication date, ranging from 1907-1936. Illustrated magazines such as Blanco y Negro, Estampa, Mundo Gráfico and Nuevo Mundo have the largest number of available fragments. This section also includes fragments in French from 1907-1934, mostly from the French Magazine Les Annales, The subject matter covered is diverse- arts, culture, economy, history, literature, politics, social events, tourism.
Series IV: Magazine Fragments, Latin America: This section contains varied selections of magazine fragments, mostly from Colombia, but also includes fragments from Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Cuba, Mexico, and Uruguay. The fragments are arranged alphabetically by name and by publication date, ranging in date from 1907-1942.The largest number of fragments are from the illustrated Colombian magazine Cromos. These fragments include articles written by Sánchez de Iriarte (Dr. Mirabel), and date from 1917-1938. The subject matter covered is diverse- arts, culture, economy, history, literature, politics, social events, tourism.
Series V: Spanish Civil War Publications, 1935-1939: Complete works and publications of the Spanish Republic and Civil War Era. Publications such as books, broadsides, bulletins, donation slips, magazine, music programs, military records, and photographs are included in this section. The publications are listed in alphabetical order either by author or title. Most of these publications are written in the English language and were published in Great Britain or the United States.
Series VI: Spanish Civil War Pamphlets, 1935-1939: The pamphlets of the Spanish Civil War era are listed in alphabetical order either by author or title. Most of these pamphlets are written in the English language and were published in Great Britain or the United States. These pamphlets represent both the left and right ideologies.
Series VII: Miscellaneous, Spain: This section includes numerous items kept by Sánchez de Iriarte, most likely collected when he was the Secretary of the Colombia Legation in Madrid. The items are ordered by topic and by alphabetical order, divided as follows:
Art Catalogs: Ceramic, drawings, painting, photographic, and sculpture catalogs of the various art exhibits Sánchez de Iriarte attended during the period from 1931 to 1934.
Music Programs: Includes various music venues Sánchez de Iriarte attended in Madrid, most of the events are from 1932.
Politics: These consist mostly of political propaganda of the Spanish left and right parties collected by Sánchez de Iriarte before the Franco Regime and a copy of the Constitution of the Spanish Republic of 1931.
Tourism: Includes pamphlets, brochures and travel guides about Spain.
Other: Includes selected clippings of people, places, and culture in Spain.
Conference Material: Contains correspondence and other documents of conferences Sánchez de Iriarte attended during his time as the Secretary of the Colombian Legation in Madrid.
Series VIII: Miscellaneous, Latin America: This series includes numerous items such as magazine clippings, manuscripts, mimeographs, typescripts, and book fragments ranging from 1883-1935 collected by Sánchez de Iriarte. The subject matter is varied- arts, economy education, government, literature, and others. There are also many undated clippings of selected short stories. These stories were probably written by Sánchez de Iriarte as Dr. Mirabel for the Colombian Magazine Cromos, though their source is unlisted.
Oversized Boxes: The oversized section contains entire books, bulletin, magazine, and newspapers about the Spanish Civil War. There is also a map of Spain showing the areas controlled by the Franco Regime and the areas controlled by the Republic.
Oversized Folder: This section includes a large folder containing three Spanish Civil War Posters.
- Series I: Newspaper Clippings, Spain
  - 1919 - May 30, 1932
    - 1919-1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - December 31, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - January 1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - February 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - March 1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - April 1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - May 1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - June 1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - July 5-18, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - July 21-31, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - August 1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - September 1-5, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - September 7-12, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - September 15-17, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - September 18-30, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - October 1931 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - November 1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - December 1931 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - January 1-5, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - January 6-13, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - January 14-31, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - February 2-11, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - February 12-21, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - February 23-25, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - February 26-28, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - March 1-4,1932 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - March 6-9, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - March 10-15, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - March 16-23, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - March 24-30, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - April 2-13, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - April 10-20, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - April 21-24, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - May 3-5, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - May 7-10, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - May 11-13, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - May 14-18, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - May 19-15, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - May 24-30, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - June 1, 1932 - December 30, 1933
    - June 1-4, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - June 5-12, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - June 15-19, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - June 21-26, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - August 1932 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - September 1-9, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - September 15-30, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - October 1932 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - November 1932 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - December 4-22, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - December 23-30, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - January 1933 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - February 1933 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - March 1933 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - April 2-16, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - April 18-29, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - May 1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - June 1-14, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - June 16-29, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - July 8-13, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - July 14-30, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - August 1933 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - September 1933 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - October 3-9, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - October 11-17, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - October 18-22, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - October 24-31, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - November 1-5, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - November 6-7, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - November 8-11, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - November 12-14, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - November 15-16, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - November 17-23, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - November 24-27, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - November 28-30, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - December 1-5, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - December 6-10, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - December 14-19, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - December 20-21, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - December 22-30, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - January 7, 1934 - November 18, 1934
    - January 7-12, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - January 13-16, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - January 25-30, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - February 1-6, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - February 8-15, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - February 16-19, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - February 21-28, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - March 1-6, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - March 7-24, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - March 25-31, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - April 2-6, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - April 7-10, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - April 11-14, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - April 15-19, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - April 20-22, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - April 23-26, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - April 27-28, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - April 29, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - May 2-5, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - May 6-10, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - May 12-17, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - May 20-24, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - May 26-31, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - June 1-4, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - June 5-8, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - June 9-12, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - June 13-19, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - June 20-24, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - June 26-30, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - July 1-6, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - July 8-12, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - July 13-29, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - August 1934 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - September 1-7, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - September 16-30, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - October 2-19, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - October 24-31, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - November 1-7, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - November 8-18, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Clippings by Subject, and Scrapbooks, February 1935 - June 29, 1943
    - February-May 1935 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - June 1935 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - July 1935 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - August 1935 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - September 1935 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - October 1935 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - November 1935 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - January 1936 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - February 6-17, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - February 19-21, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - February 22-29, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - March 4-13, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - March 15-18, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - March 21-29, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - April 4-7, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - April 10-11, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - April 12-30, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - May 2-17, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - May 28-31, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - June 1936 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - July 1-10, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - July 12-19, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - October-November 1936 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - 1937-1939 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - June 29, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Tourism in Spain (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Clippings in French, 1920-1936
    - Newspaper Clippings in French, 1920-1927 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Newspaper Clippings in French, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Newspaper Clippings in French, February-May 1935 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Newspaper Clippings in French, June-December 1935 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Newspaper Clippings in French, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Scrapbooks, 1935-1939
    - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, Scrapbook, Europe and Latin America; Articles about History, 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Scrapbook, Europe and Latin America; Guerra Civil Española: Farsa de la No-Intervención (Spanish Civil War: Farce of the Non-Intervention), 1936-1938 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Scrapbook, Europe and Latin America; Guerra Civil Española, Fotos Caricaturas, Mapas, Planos (Spanish Civil War: Photos, Caricatures, Maps, Blueprints), 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Scrapbook, Europe and Latin America; La Guerra en el País Vasco (War in Basque Nation), 1936-1939 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Scrapbook, Latin America and Spain; El Frente Popular y sus victorias en Francia y España, 1936 (The Popular Front and its Victories in France and Spain, 1936) (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Scrapbook, Latin America and Spain; Guerra Civil Española: Sobre personajes varios, pros y contras (Spanish Civil War: About Various Important Figures; Pros and Cons), 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Scrapbook, Spain; Guerra Civil Española: Los Santos y la Guerra (Spanish Civil War: The Saints and the War), 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Series II: Newspaper Clippings, Latin America
  - 1910- December 1931
    - 1910 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1915 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1916 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1917 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1918 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - March-August 1919 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - December 1919 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - January-May 1920 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - June-December 1920 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1921 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - 1922 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - January-June 1923 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - July-November 1923 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - 1924 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - 1925 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - January-August 1926 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - September-November 1926 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - January-March 1927 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - May 1927 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - July-December 1927 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - January 1928 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - February 4-14, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - February 18-27, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - March 1928 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - April-September 1928 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - October 1928 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - January 1929 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - February 1929 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - March 1929 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - April 1929 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - May 1929 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - June 1929 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - August 1929 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - September 1929 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - October 1929 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - November 1929 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - December 1929 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - January-February 1930 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - March 1930 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - May-June 1930 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - July-September 1930 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - February 1931 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - April 1931 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - May-August 1931 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - September 1931 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - October-December 1931 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - January 1932- December 1936
    - January 1932 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - March 1932 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - April-September 1932 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - December 1932 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - January-September 1933 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - October-December 1933 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 1934 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - January-February 1935 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - March 1-18, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - March 21-30, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - April 2-13, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - April 16-27, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - May 1935 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - June 1935 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - July 1935 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - August 1935 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - September 1935 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - October-December 1935 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - January 1936 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - February 3-18, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - February 19-37, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - March 1936 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - April 1936 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - May 5-10, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - May 18-31, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - June 1-14, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - June 18-29, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - July 1936 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - August 5-24, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - August 25-29, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - September 5-11, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - September 19-28, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - October 1-14, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - October 21-25, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - October 26-31, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - November 1-8, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - November 13-26, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - December 1936 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Clippings by Subject, and Scrapbooks, 1937-1946
    - January 2-6, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - January 13-26, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - February 1937 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - March 1937 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - April 1937 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - May 5-14, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - May 23-27, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - May 28-30, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - June 3-17, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - June 25-30, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - July 1-12, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - July 14-23, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - July 24-31, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - August-November 1937 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - December 1937 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - January 3-17, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - January 20-31, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - February-March 1938 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - April 1938 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - May-July 1938 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - August 1938 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - September-December 1938 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - January-May 1939 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - June-July 1939 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - August-December 1939 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - 1940 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - February-July 1941 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - August-November 1941 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - February-June 1942 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - September-November 1942 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - 1943 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - January-June 1944 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - July-December 1944 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - 1945 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - 1946 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Colombian Cities (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - General Santander (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Historia del Teatro en Bogotá (History of Theater in Bogotá), 1923 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Literature (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Literature (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Notable people from Colombia (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings: Gold 1913-1920 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings Scrapbooks, 1919-1935
    - Articles about H.G. Wells, 1920-1931 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Articles about Money, 1919-1928 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Articles about Diplomacy, 1920-1935 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Bancos (Banking), 1917-1920 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - El Oro (The Gold), 1918-1920 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Presupuestos (Budgets), 1916 (Box 7, Folder 48)
- Series III: Magazine Fragments, Spain 1914-1936
  - A-E
    - ABC, Extraordinary Issue, May 31, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Aero Club de Galicia A.C.G (Galicia Aero club) pgs. 23-26, April 1933 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Álbum Nacional (National Album), 1931 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Aragón, pgs. 105-106, June 1931 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Aragón, pgs. 67-68 and 81-86, April-May 1934 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Aragón, pgs. 153-158, September 1934 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Blanco y Negro (White and Black), pgs. 9-10 and 26-31, April 3, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 7)